Haneul Yoo

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

📞 +82-10-5269-2387 | 🖂 haneul.yoo@kaist.ac.kr | 🏕 haneul-yoo.github.io | 🖸 haneul-yoo | **in** haneulyoo | 💆 HaneulYoo13

About ___

Haneul Yoo is a Ph.D. student advised by Professor Alice Oh in the School of Computing at KAIST. Her research interest primarily lies in the field of natural language processing and machine learning. In particular, she is dedicated to (1) data-centric and multilingual NLP and (2) LLM-driven education innovation. She believes there are still myriads of underrepresented languages in NLP, and our efforts on low-resource languages can build more culturally-diverse language models. She also believes recent advances in AI can assist language learners, and researchers can leverage them to enhance NLP data and techniques as well.

Education

Daejeon, Korea

Ph.D. IN SCHOOL OF COMPUTING Sep 2022 - CURRENT

· Advisor: Alice Oh

KAIST Daejeon, Korea

M.S. IN SCHOOL OF COMPUTING Sep 2020 - Aug 2022

· Advisor: Alice Oh

Ajou University Suwon, Korea

B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Mar 2017 - Aug 2020 B.S. IN DIGITAL MEDIA

• University of Wisconsin - Stout, WI, USA — Semester Abroad Winter 2018

Experience _____

Upstage Remote

DATA MANAGEMENT INTERN Aug 2023 - Nov 2023

· Construction and management of Korean evaluation benchmark for LLMs

• Advisor: Taehwan Oh and Jiyoon Han

Naver AI Lab Sungnam, Korea Mar 2023 - Jul 2023

VISITING STUDENT

Construction and management of KoBBQ, Korean bias benchmark for question answering

· Advisor: Hwaran Lee

LAMDA Lab Suwon, Korea

RESEARCH INTERN Mar 2020 - Aug 2020

• Study of Deep Learning Model for Bio-signal (EEG) Analysis

• Advisor: Jungryul Seo and Kyung-Ah Sohn

KEPRI Daejeon, Korea

Sep 2019 - Feb 2020

· Development of application services utilizing electric used power data

· Advisor: Moonsuk Choi

CSIRO QLD, Australia Jul 2019 - Aug 2019 RESEARCH INTERN

• Development of Convolutional deep neural network for detecting cattle in images/videos

Advisor: Brano Kusy

Indielist Suwon, Korea

SOFTWARE ENGINEER & CO-FOUNDER Jul 2018 - Jun 2019

· Establishment of an independent music platform and development of iOS application services

Publications _____ * denotes equal contributions

ChEDDAR: Student-ChatGPT Dialogue in EFL Writing Education

preprint Jieun Han*, **Haneul Yoo***, Junho Myung, Minsun Kim, Tak Yeon Lee, So-Yeon Ahn, and Alice Oh Sep 2023

OCTOBER 1, 2023 HANEUL YOO · CURRICULUM VITAE

FABRIC: Automated Scoring and Feedback Generation for Essays

Jieun Han*, **Haneul Yoo***, Junho Myung, Minsun Kim, Hyunseung Lim, Yoonsu Kim, Tak Yeon Lee, Hwajung Hong, JUHO KIM, SO-YEON AHN, AND ALICE OH

under review

KoBBQ: Korean Bias Benchmark for Question Answering

JIHO JIN*, JISEON KIM*, NAYEON LEE*, **HANEUL YOO***, ALICE OH, HWARAN LEE

preprint Jul 2023

Rethinking Annotation: Can Language Learners Contribute?

HANEUL YOO, RIFKI AFINA PUTRI, CHANGYOON LEE, YOUNGIN LEE, SO-YEON AHN, DONGYEOP KANG, AND ALICE OH

ACL 2023 Jul 2023

RECIPE: How to Integrate ChatGPT into EFL Writing Education

JIEUN HAN*, HANEUL YOO*, YOONSU KIM, JUNHO MYUNG, MINSUN KIM, HYUNSEUNG LIM, JUHO KIM, TAK YEON LEE, HWAJUNG HONG, SO-YEON AHN, AND ALICE OH

Jul 2023

Translating Hanja Historical Documents to Understandable Korean and English

Juhee Son*, Jiho Jin*, **Haneul Yoo**, JinYeong Bak, Kyunghyun Cho, and Alice Oh

EMNLP 2022, Findings Dec 2022

L@S 2023, Work in Progress

HUE: Pretrained Model and Dataset for Understanding Hanja Documents of Ancient Korea

HANEUL YOO, JIHO JIN, JUHEE SON, JINYEONG BAK, KYUNGHYUN CHO, AND ALICE OH

NAACL 2022, Findings Jul 2022

EMNLP 2021, Findings

Knowledge-Enhanced Evidence Retrieval for Counterargument Generation YOHAN JO, HANEUL YOO, JINYEONG BAK, ALICE OH, CHRIS REED, AND EDUARD HOVY

Nov 2021

KICS Summer Conference 2020

Image-based Deep Learning Approach for EEG Signal Classification

HANEUL YOO, JUNGRYUL SEO, AND KYUNG-AH SOHN

Aug 2020

Proposal and Simulation of Optimal Electric Vehicle Routing Algorithm

MOONSUK CHOI, INJI CHOI, MINHAE JANG, AND HANEUL YOO

KFPCO 2020 Mar 2020

Talks ___

Guest Lecturer AI Tech Boostcamp, "Several Aspects that We Should Consider about Data-Centric NLP" (May 2023)

Guest Lecturer Al Tech Boostcamp, "The Data You Constructed, Are You Sure It's Okay?" (Dec 2022)

Teaching Experiences ____

Al Tech Boostcamp (Spring 2023, Fall 2022) at NAVER Connect Foundation

Machine Learning for Natural Language Processing (Fall 2023), Al Ethics (Spring 2023), Al and Its Social Impact (Spring 2023), TA

KAIST SoC Colloquium (Fall 2021), Machine Learning (Fall 2022, Spring 2021) at KAIST

Python (Spring 2020) at Suwon Information Science High School, Java (Spring 2019) at Maetan High School Teacher

Academic Services

Volunteer FAccT (2022), COLING (2022) **Reviewer** NeurIPS (2021, 2023), EMNLP (2022)

Honors and Awards

KAIST Support Scholarship

Graduation with Honors

SUMMA CUM LAUDE (1ST PLACE)

KAIST

Sep 2020 - Current

Ajou University

Aug 2020

Outstanding Volunteer Award Gyeonggi Volunteer Center

Jun 2020

KIPA

Special Prize RIXPO 2019

Excellence Award

Nov 2019

Nov 2019

CREATIVE START-UP COMPETITION

Academic Excellence Scholarship Asan Foundation Mar 2017 - Aug 2020

References _____

Alice Oh Professor in School of Computing, KAIST